Hi, this is Matt Baker. When it comes to
political dynasties in Canada, most
people only know about the Trudeau
family, which of course includes the
recent prime minister Justin Trudeau, as
well as his late father Pierre Trudeau,
who also served as prime minister. Both
of them belong to the Liberal Party,
which is considered center left in
contrast to the Conservative Party,
which is center right. But Canada also
has another party which is even further
to the left, the NDP or New Democratic
Party. Until recently, it was led by
Jugmeat Singh. But after the party's
poor showing in last year's election, he
resigned and therefore the NDP is
currently in the middle of a leadership
race. The three front runners are
Heather McFersonen, who is the more
pragmatic candidate closer to what you
might expect from a liberal, Rob Ashton,
who is a union leader focused on workers
rights, and Avi Lewis, who is perhaps
the most ideological and who has been
compared to Zoran Mandani. But what a
lot of people don't know about Avi Lewis
is that he's actually a fourthg
generation member of a family that has
been involved in Canadian politics for
over 100 years. A family that includes
not only politicians but several
prominent authors and activists. So
today I'm going to show you the family
tree of the Lewis family. Let's start
with Moa Lewis who at the time of his
birth in 1888 was named Moa Loss. Like
many Eastern European Jews from that
generation, he was born in a smalletle,
which was at the time a part of the
Russian Empire. As a young adult, he
became involved with the Jewish Labor
Bund, which was a socialist party made
up of secular Jews. Unlike some other
Jewish groups at the time, members of
the Bund were not Zionists. They wanted
to remain in Europe, help establish a
socialist society there, while at the
same time maintaining their Jewish
culture and identity. For this reason,
they promoted Yiddish as the language of
the Jewish people, not Hebrew. However,
after the success of the Russian
Revolution, the Bolsheviks wanted Jews
to completely assimilate, something that
Moa Law and other Bundists disagreed
with. At this point, things got very
dangerous for them and therefore in
1921, Moisha decided to take his family
and immigrate to Canada. Upon arrival,
the family anglicized their surname to
Lewis and Moa sometimes went by Morris.
Once in Canada, he remained active in
socialist circles, joining both the
Jewish labor committee and the workman's
circle. His son David was the next
person in the family to get involved in
politics. After completing his initial
studies in Canada, he got a scholarship
to Oxford where he solidified his
anti-communist pro-ocialist views,
becoming involved in the early days of
the British Labor Party. He was even
offered a seat in the UK House of
Commons, but turned it down, opting
instead to return to Canada, where he
became the national secretary of the
recently formed Cooperative Commonwealth
Federation, the predecessor of the NDP.
Around the same time, he married Sophie
Carson, the daughter of Hyman Carson and
Edith Epstein. Now, at this point, I
need to say a few words about the
surname Epstein, because it also showed
up on Zoran Mdani's family tree, and a
lot of people made comments about it.
What you need to know is that Epstein is
a very common Jewish surname. So, in
most cases, like this one, there's no
connection to Jeffrey Epstein. So, out
of respect for the victims, no silly
comments, please. During the 1950s,
David Lewis practiced labor law while at
the same time continuing his involvement
in the CCF. Then, in 1962, after the CCF
became the NDP, he ran for election and
became a federal MP. Now, the first
leader of the NDP was Tommy Douglas,
known as the father of Canadian
healthcare. Interestingly, his daughter
Shirley, who was an actress and who was
also very active in the US civil rights
movement, married Donald Sutherland, the
famous actor. Together, they became the
parents of Kefir Sutherland, yet another
famous actor. Anyhow, in 1971, Tommy
Douglas retired as leader of the NDP and
was replaced by David Lewis, who served
until 1975. After this, Ed Broadbent
took the reigns and helped the party
grow even more. The next generation
includes Steven Lewis who became an
elected politician around the same time
as his father. Although in Steven's case
it was at the provincial level as a
member of the Ontario Parliament. Later
he became the leader of the Ontario NDP
and then after that he served as
Canada's ambassador to the UN as well as
in several positions relating to the
AIDS crisis in Africa. He is married to
Michelle Lansberg, who is an
accomplished activist in her own right.
As a writer working for major
publications such as the Globe and Mail
and Toronto Star, she was among the
first Canadian journalists to talk about
sexual harassment in the workplace.
Steven's brother Michael and sister
Janet were both involved with the
Ontario NDP on the organizational side
and his sister Nenah is notable in that
she's the business partner and wife of
the famous architect Daniel Liebuskin,
designer of the Jewish Museum in Berlin
among many other projects. Let's now go
down one more generation. Like his
mother, Avi Lewis has so far worked
mostly as a journalist hosting programs
for both the CBC and Alazer. Although
now, like I say, he's currently running
to become the next leader of the federal
NDP. His wife is the famous author Naomi
Klene. Interestingly, the rabbi who
married Avi and Naomi is the same rabbi
who married my wife and I. Anyhow, Naomi
Klein often gets confused with Naomi
Wolf. So, take note that Klene is the
one who wrote the anti-globalization
and anti- capitalist books, no logo, the
shock doctrine, and this changes
everything. Both she and Avi are also
known for their criticism of Israel and
for being longtime supporters of the
Palestinian cause. Something that I feel
is important to point out as many people
seem to think that all Jews are ardent
Zionists, which is actually not true.
Avi has two sisters. Elana was recently
appointed as the head of Rainbow
Railroad, a charity that helps LGBT
people escape violence in their home
countries. She was previously married to
Lorraine Sagato, the lead singer of the
Parachute Club. Jenny is a casting
director together with her partner Sarah
Kay. They recently cast the leads for
the hit show Heated Rivalry. Finally,
I'd like to point out Naomi Klein's
brother Seth, who is a climate change
activist, and her mother, Bonnie Sher,
who is a disability rights activist. So,
lots of interesting people on this tree.
All right, so that was a look at the
Lewis family, one of the most prominent
political families on the Canadian left.
Take note that the NDP leadership vote
will happen on March 29th. So that's
when we'll find out whether or not the
NDP will get the grandson of a previous
leader as their new leader. Thanks for
watching.